Preliminary Guide to the Herbert Spencer Harned Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Herbert Spencer Harned papers
1912-1978
MS 1022
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Miscellaneous scientific papers and proposals, an autobiographical essay, a biographical article by Julian Sturtevant, reminiscences of students, a bibliography of Herbert Spencer Harned's works (1912-1963), an outline for a science course at Yale University, and a few items of correspondence make up this collection.
Harned, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer), 1888-1969
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Spencer Harned, chemist, was born on December 2, 1888, the son of Thomas Biggs and Augusta Anna (Traubel) Harned. His father was a successful lawyer and his mother an abolitionist. Both parents were close friends of Walt Whitman.
Herbert Harned received a B.A. degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1909, a B.S. in 1910, and a Ph.D. in 1913. He was an instructor at the University of Pennsylvania from 1913 to 1917, an assistant professor from 1917 to 1926, and a professor from 1926 to 1928. During World War I, Harned served as a captain in the chemical war service of the U.S. Army. In 1928 Herbert Harned came to Yale and was a professor of chemistry until his retirement in 1957. From 1943 to 1945 he was a group leader for the Manhattan Project and from 1950 to 1965 served as a consultant for the Oak Ridge National Laboratory.
Herbert Harned died on July 29, 1969.
Scope and Contents
Miscellaneous scientific papers and proposals, an autobiographical essay, a biographical article by Julian Sturtevant, reminiscences of students, a bibliography of Herbert Spencer Harned's works (1912-1963), an outline for a science course at Yale University, and a few items of correspondence make up this collection.
Chemistry; Science; Chemists; Educators; Harned, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer), 1888-1969; Sturtevant, Julian M. (Julian Munson), 1908-2005; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Sterling Chemistry Laboratory
- Inventory
  - General correspondence, 1922-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence relating to H. S. Harned, 1955-1960, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, financial statements and reports relating to contract At (30-1) 1375, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and proposals relating to Science I, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Summary report relating to research at the Sterling Chemistry Laboratory, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings (abstract), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical data, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autobiographical data, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Recollections of students and colleagues, 1927, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bibliography, 1912-1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial papers, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)